<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="IntroductionToCounterpoint">
    <title>Introduction to Counterpoint</title>
    <section xml:id="SpeciesCounterpoint">
        <title>Species Counterpoint</title>
        <p>The seminal composition text, <pubtitle>Gradus ad Parnassum</pubtitle> (1725), by Johann Joseph Fux, teaches contrapuntal composition through <q>species counterpoint.</q> <term>Species counterpoint</term><idx><h>species counterpoint</h><h>definition of</h></idx> uses simple rhythmic values and teaches composers how to write one, two, three, or four notes against a larger value, usually a whole note. In this text, we will focus on writing for two voices. In a semester-long college course in counterpoint, one typically learns to write for up to four voices.</p>
        <p><term>Counterpoint</term><idx><h>counterpoint</h><h>definition of</h></idx> can be thought of as the simultaneous sounding of two or more melodic lines. An example is shown below.</p>
        <figure>
            <figure>
            <caption>Bach, J.S., <pubtitle>Well-Tempered Clavier, Book I</pubtitle>, Fugue 3 in C-sharp major, BWV 848</caption>
            <idx><h>Bach, J.S.</h><h><pubtitle>Well-Tempered Clavier, Book I</pubtitle></h><h>Fugue 3 in C-sharp major, BWV 848</h></idx>
            <sbsgroup>
                <sidebyside>
                    <image source="images/unit10/ctrpt-c-sharp-fugue-mels">
                        <description/>
                    </image>
                </sidebyside>
                <sidebyside margins="37%">
                    <video youtube="YGHj2CmNz0E" start="0" end="15" play-at="select" preview="generic"/>
                </sidebyside>
            </sbsgroup>
        </figure>
        <p>Textures made of counterpoint are called <q>contrapuntal</q> and can be contrasted with melody<ndash/>accompaniment textures, which are called <q>homophonic.</q></p>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="FirstSpecies">
        <title>First Species</title>
        <p>In first species, we will write note against note counterpoint in whole notes. You will be given a melody, called the <foreign>cantus</foreign> firmus (abbreviated <q><foreign>c.f.</foreign></q> and meaning <q>preexisting melody</q>), against which you will write a counterpoint.</p>
        <figure>
            <caption/>
            <image source="images/unit10/ctrpt-1st-sp-cf-example"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Fux enumerates several rules to follow to write in proper sixteenth<ndash/>century style (the style of Palestrina). Since this is a brief introduction to writing in species counterpoint, the rules below are slightly modified and simplified. You would likely follow stricter rules in an semester<ndash/>long course in counterpoint.</p>
        <ol>
            <li>
                <p>Begin with an octave or unison.</p>
        <sidebyside>
                    <image source="images/unit10/ctrpt-1st-sp-start-w-8">
                        <description/>
                    </image>
                </sidebyside>
            </li>
            <li><p>End on an octave or unison.</p></li>
            <li><p>Approach the ending octave or unison by contrary motion; one of the parts will end with <scaledeg>7</scaledeg><ndash/><scaledeg>8</scaledeg> while the other ends with <scaledeg>2</scaledeg><ndash/><scaledeg>1</scaledeg>.
            <sidebyside>
                    <image source="images/unit10/ctrpt-1st-sp-end-6-8">
                        <description/>
                    </image>
                </sidebyside>
                <ol>
                    <li><p>If the example is in G mixolydian, D dorian, or A aeolian, use a sharp to create the leading tone (F<sharp/>, G<sharp/>, and C<sharp/> respectively).</p></li>
                </ol>
            </p></li>

            <li><p>Create consonant harmonic intervals in each measure (unisons, 3rds 5ths, 6ths, and their compound versions<mdash/>10ths, 12ths, 13ths, etc.). Dissonances (2nds, 4ths, 7ths) are not allowed in first species counterpoint.
                <ol>
                    <li><p><q>Imperfect</q> consonances (3rds and 6ths) can be approached in any manner
                        <ol>
                            <li><p>Do not use more than three consecutive 3rds or 6ths</p></li>
                        </ol>
                    </p></li>
                    <li><p><q>Perfect</q> consonances (unisons, 5ths, 8ves, 12ths) may only be approached in <em>contrary</em> motion in order to avoid direct 5ths and direct 8ves (you may wish to review the <xref ref="TypesOfMotion" text="title">types of motion</xref>).</p></li>
                </ol>
            </p></li>
            <li><p>Only the following leaps are allowed: 3rds, 4ths, 5ths, ascending minor sixths, and 8ves (review the <xref ref="RulesOfMelody" text="title">Rules of Melody</xref> with regard to direction changes after leaps).</p></li>
            <li><p>Avoid melodically outlining a tritone by changing directions at two turning points in a melody.</p></li>
        </ol>
        
        





    </section>
    <section xml:id="VoiceLeadingNeapolitanChord">
        <title>Voice Leading the Neapolitan Chord</title>
        <p></p>
        

    </section>
    <section xml:id="VoiceLeadingAugmentedSixthChords">
        <title>Voice Leading Augmented Sixth Chords</title>
        <p></p>
        
    </section>
    <exercises xml:id="IntroductionToCounterpointExercises">
        <title>Practice Exercises</title>
        <exercisegroup>
            <introduction>
                <p>Day One</p>
            </introduction>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Analyze the figured bass to provide Roman numerals in the blanks below the staff, then voice lead the progression. Include the key signature.</p>
                    <sidebyside>
                        <image source="images/unit9/PRAC-EXER-vl-sec-fig-bass">
                            <description/>
                        </image>
                    </sidebyside>
                </statement>
                <answer>
                    <sidebyside>
                        <image source="images/unit9/PRAC-EXER-vl-sec-fig-bass-ANSWER">
                            <description/>
                        </image>
                    </sidebyside>
                </answer>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Voice lead the following Roman numeral progression. Include the key signature. Add the following non<ndash/>chord tones: 1 suspension, 1 passing tone, 1 anticipation, and 3 neighbor tones.</p>
                    <sidebyside>
                        <image source="images/unit9/PRAC-EXER-vl-sec-rn">
                            <description/>
                        </image>
                    </sidebyside>
                </statement>
                <answer>
                    <sidebyside>
                        <image source="images/unit9/PRAC-EXER-vl-sec-rn-ANSWER">
                            <description/>
                        </image>
                    </sidebyside>
                    <p>Notice that the chords on beats 5 and 6 are consecutive first inversion chords (even though one is a 7th chord), therefore the third is doubled on <chord root="I" bps="6"/> to avoid parallel fifths.</p>
                </answer>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
        <exercisegroup>
            <introduction>
                <p>Day Two</p>
            </introduction>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Analyze the figured bass to provide Roman numerals in the blanks below the staff, then voice lead the progressions in chorale style. Include the key signatures. Include one suspension in each measure.</p>
                    <sidebyside>
                        <image source="images/unit9/PRAC-EXER-mm-and-N6">
                            <description/>
                        </image>
                    </sidebyside>
                </statement>
                <answer>
                    <sidebyside>
                        <image source="images/unit9/PRAC-EXER-mm-and-N6-ANSWER">
                            <description/>
                        </image>
                    </sidebyside>
                </answer>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
        <exercisegroup>
            <introduction>
                <p>Day Three</p>
            </introduction>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Analyze the figured bass to provide Roman numerals in the blanks below the staff. Voice lead the progressions in chorale style. Include the key signatures.</p>
                    <sidebyside>
                        <image source="images/unit9/PRAC-EXER-vl-aug-6">
                            <description/>
                        </image>
                    </sidebyside>
                </statement>
                <answer>
                    <sidebyside>
                        <image source="images/unit9/PRAC-EXER-vl-aug-6-ANSWER">
                            <description/>
                        </image>
                    </sidebyside>
                </answer>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
        <exercisegroup>
            <introduction>
                <p>Day Four</p>
            </introduction>
            <exercise>
                <statement>
                    <p>Voice lead the following Roman numeral progression. Include the key signature. Add the following non<ndash/>chord tones: an escape tone, a 4<ndash/>3 suspension, an anticipation, and a passing tone.</p>
                    <sidebyside>
                        <image source="images/unit9/HW-vl-aug-6-A-flat-maj-rom-num">
                            <description/>
                        </image>
                    </sidebyside>
                </statement>
                <answer>
                    <sidebyside>
                        <image source="images/unit9/HW-vl-aug-6-A-flat-maj-rom-num-ANSWER">
                            <description/>
                        </image>
                    </sidebyside>
                </answer>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>

        <conclusion>
            <p>Click <url href="../hw/MT21C_HW_44.pdf">here to download the first homework assignment for this chapter.</url></p>
            <p>Click <url href="../hw/MT21C_HW_45.pdf">here to download the second homework assignment for this chapter.</url></p>
            <p>Click <url href="../hw/MT21C_HW_46.pdf">here to download the third homework assignment for this chapter.</url></p>
            <p>Click <url href="../hw/MT21C_HW_47.pdf">here to download the fourth homework assignment for this chapter.</url></p>
            <p>Click <url href="../hw/MT21C_Unit_9_Practice_Test.pdf">here to download the Unit 9 Practice Test.</url></p>
        </conclusion>
    </exercises>
</chapter>